Guide to the Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, 1834-1969, bulk 1890-1929. RL.00328
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1871-1941 and undated; 1893-1923; 37.5 Linear Feet
  - Letters, 1872-1941
    - 1902 September 23, oversize (Box 123, Folder 4)
      B. F. Taylor to B. N. Duke: land plat for property at 5th Avenue and East 76th Street, New York, NY (Frank E. Forbes, surveyor).
    - 1903 January-April, 12 folders (Box 20)
    - 1903 May-September, 15 folders (Box 21)
      Includes letters from Jonathan C. Kilgo and Greensboro Female College Alumnae Association members regarding the school's funding crisis and possible closure; and correspondence with J. B. Cobb and A. B. Carrington related to American Tobacco Company's southern tobacco markets, including sales statements for the 1902 tobacco crop.
    - 1903 July 31, oversize (Box 123, Folder 4)
      Mary Davis Allen to B.N. Duke: ground plan for Louisburg Female College pantry.
    - 1903 October-1904 March, 16 folders (Box 22)
      Includes letters from Walter H. Page and Trinity College trustees regarding the John S. Bassett affair; correspondence related to the Coleman Manufacturing Company; the smallpox outbreak in Durham; Brodie L. Duke's divorce and child custody case; and fundraising for Kittrell College.
    - 1904 April-September, 16 folders (Box 23)
      Includes letters related to Brodie L. Duke's divorce and child custody case; letters from J. M. Currin regarding tobacco operations in Australia; and a letter from George W. Watts about the establishment of the Durham Loan & Trust Company.
    - 1904 October-1905 March, 15 folders (Box 24)
      Includes letters from Walter H. Page and Trinity College trustees regarding the John S. Bassett affair.
    - 1904 November 12, oversize (Box 123, Folder 4)
      Smith-Courtney to J. E. Stagg: floor plan for proposed addition to Washington Duke's residence, Durham, NC.
    - 1905 April-August, 13 folders (Box 25)
      Includes correspondence related to the chartering of Citizen's National Bank of Durham and the illness and death of Washington Duke.
    - 1905 September-December, 13 folders (Box 26)
      Includes proposal to enlarge the Southern Conservatory of Music (Durham, NC).
    - 1906 January, 6 folders (Box 27)
      Includes correspondence related to Angier B. Duke's accident at Carteret Lodge; letter from Condé Nast describing an investment opportunity in the Home Pattern Company; and a letter from Bishop W. A. Candler regarding mission in Cuba.
    - 1906 February-April, 11 folders (Box 27)
      Includes correspondence regarding the sale of the Coleman Manufacturing Company property (Concord, NC) and funding for a "Duke Memorial Hall" at Kittrell College.
    - 1906 May-October, 18 folders (Box 28)
    - 1906 November-1907 January, 11 folders (Box 29)
    - 1907? January 22, scroll (Box 63)
      Rosa Parrish to Sarah P. Duke, sent from Japan.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Fragile—please ask for staff assistance in handling this item.
    - 1907 February-March, 6 folders (Box 29)
      Includes correspondence related to pledges to the Durham, NC, YMCA building.
    - 1907 April-September, 17 folders (Box 30)
    - 1907 October-1908 February, 17 folders (Box 31)
    - 1908 March-June, 14 folders (Box 32)
      Includes letters from Charles C. Hook regarding construction plans for Duke's new Durham home (Four Acres) and correspondence related to the dedication of the Washington Duke statue at Trinity College.
    - 1908 July-1908 October, 14 folders (Box 33)
    - 1908 November-1909 February, 14 folders (Box 34)
      Includes letters related to the debt of Daniel Lindsay Russell, and letters concerning the purchase of the Odell Manufacturing Company property and founding of Locke Cotton Mills in Concord, NC.
    - 1909 March-July, 17 folders (Box 35)
    - 1909 August-October, 11 folders (Box 36)
    - 1909 October 4, oversize blueprints (Box 123, Folder 5)
      H. Buckenham to B. N. Duke: blueprint proposal for new athletic grounds at Trinity College.
    - 1909 November, 5 folders (Box 36)
      Includes correspondence and plans related to the relocation of "The Terrace" (former Duke residence, Durham, NC).
    - 1909 November, oversize (Box 123, Folder 6)
      N. Underwood to B. N. Duke: plans for new porch for relocated Durham, NC house ("The Terrace"); C. P. H. Gilbert to B. N. Duke: land plat of B. N. Duke property at 5th Avenue and E. 89th Street, New York, NY.
    - 1909 December-1910 March, 17 folders (Box 37)
    - 1910 April-1910 June, 12 folders (Box 38)
    - 1910 July-September, 15 folders (Box 39)
    - 1910 October-December, 17 folders (Box 40)
      Includes a letter from the Tuskeegee Institute, signed by Booker T. Washington, soliciting donations to support students.
    - circa 1908-1910, 1 folders (Box 40)
    - 1911 January-March, 16 folders (Box 41)
      Includes correspondence with John Merrick, James E. Shepard and others related to contributions by James B. Duke and Benjamin N. Duke to Lincoln Hospital and the National Religious Training School and Chautauqua for the Colored Race; letters regarding the Main Building (Washington Duke Building) fire at Trinity College; and letters and statements related to the Trinity College building fund and campus construction.
    - 1911 April-June, 14 folders (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence with Ceasar Cone and others regarding Cone's buyout of Asheville Cotton Mills stock and ensuing dispute with B. Frank Mebane (1911 April-June); letters and invoices related to Duke family portraits by Joaquin Sorolla (1911 June); and letters and statements related to the Trinity College building fund and campus construction.
    - 1911 July-November, 14 folders (Box 43)
      Includes correspondence about the death and estate of John C. Angier; letters regarding the heating system for Lincoln Hospital (Durham, NC); and correspondence related to the Trinity College building fund and construction of new dormitories.
    - 1911 December-1912 January, 12 folders (Box 44)
      Includes correspondence with C. W. Toms and W. W. Flowers related to the construction of Memorial Methodist Church (Durham, NC); and letters from James A. Thomas regarding the conversion of his American Tobacco Company securities, with some observations on events in China.
    - 1912 February-April, 14 folders (Box 45)
      Includes correspondence related to the construction of Memorial Methodist Church (Durham, NC) and the Administration Building and new dormitory at Trinity College.
    - 1912 May-July, 12 folders (Box 46)
    - 1912 August, 4 folders (Box 47)
      Includes correspondence with William P. Few regarding the naming of new Trinity College dormitories after Thomas Jarvis and Charles Aycock.
    - 1912 September-November, 11 folders (Box 47)
    - 1912 December-1913 January, 9 folders (Box 48)
      Includes letter from W. A. Erwin discussing proposed legislation of the Child Labor Committee.
    - 1913 January 15, oversize (Box 161, Folder 1)
      Hornor & Company to B. N. Duke: map of Long Island Sound, New York (Pell & Chambers, Real Estate).
    - 1913 February, 4 folders (Box 48)
    - 1913 March, 5 folders (Box 49)
    - 1913 March 29, 2 items; oversize blueprints (Box 161, Folder 1)
      W. S. Lee to B. N. Duke: land plats of Charlotte and Dilworth, NC and the A.C. Springs & Company property, Charlotte, NC.
    - 1913 April, 5 folders (Box 49)
    - 1913 May, 5 folders (Box 50)
    - 1913 May 5, 3 items; oversize (Box 161, Folder 1)
      D. M. Barringer to B. N. Duke: curves of pig iron production for the world and the United States (from Manufacturers Record); Texas Iron Association iron ore deposits diagram; blueprint map showing districts with iron ore deposits in Cass County, Texas
    - 1913 June, 4 folders (Box 50)
    - 1913 July, 4 folders (Box 50)
      Includes correspondence related to a contribution by James B. Duke and Benjamin N. Duke to the endowment of Trinity College.
    - 1913 August-October, 13 folders (Box 51)
    - 1913 November-1914 January, 13 folders (Box 52)
    - 1914 February-April, 14 folders (Box 53)
      Includes correspondence with John C. Kilgo and others regarding the official relationship of Trinity College with the Methodist Church (1914 April).
    - 1914 May-July, 13 folders (Box 54)
    - 1914 August-November, 14 folders (Box 55)
      Includes correspondence regarding the Trinity Land Company's sale of timber rights in Carteret County, NC; letter from James E. Shepard seeking assistance with the debt of the National Training School (1914 October); and a letter from Laura Drake Gill regarding a proposal for the establishment of a coordinate college for women at Trinity College (1914 November).
    - 1914 December-1915 March, 15 folders (Box 56)
      Includes letter from Julian S. Carr regarding the North Carolina Children's Home (1914 December); and a letter from James E. Shepard seeking assistance with the debt of the National Training School (1915 February).
    - 1915 April-July, 12 folders (Box 57)
      Includes letters related to travel arrangements for Angier B. Duke and Cordelia Biddle Duke (1915 April), and Mary Duke Biddle and Anthony J. Duke Biddle, Jr. (1915 May) after the couples' weddings; letters from James E. Shepard regarding mortgage payments for the National Training School (1915 June); and letters regarding the Lincoln Hospital Nurses' Home and Kittrell College (1915 July).
    - 1915 August-December and circa 1915, 14 folders (Box 58)
      Includes letters from W. R. Perkins and P. D. Gold regarding The National Drama Corporation and Thomas Dixon, Jr.'s film "The Fall of a Nation"; correspondence from Jonathan R. Hawkins regarding funding for Kittrell College and the African Methodist Episcopal Church; and letters regarding the construction of the stone wall around Trinity College.
    - 1916 January-1918 May, 16 folders (Box 59)
      Includes correspondence related to the National Drama Corporation and "The Fall of a Nation"; letters from J. C. Thorn regarding the Durham Realty Corporation; a letter from James H. Southgate discussing land in Orange County, NC; and a letter from John Merrick discussing property for a new Lincoln Hospital site.
    - 1918 June-1919 December, 6 folders (Box 60)
      Includes several letters from Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr. to B. N. Duke, some of which express Biddle's opinions on the League of Nations (1918 May, 1918 December-1919 February); and a typescript copy of a personal letter from James B. Duke to B. N. Duke (February 1919).
    - circa 1890s-1910s, 2 folders (Box 60)
    - 1920 January-1923 April, 7 folders (Box 60)
      Includes correspondence between Duke and William P. Few regarding the construction of Southgate Residence Hall and Alumni Memorial Gymnasium at Trinity College.
    - 1923 May-1928 April, 13 folders (Box 61)
      Includes correspondence related to Duke's health and financial contributions to various institutions, including Buies Creek Academy (later Campbell University), Duke's Chapel (Braggtown, Durham, NC), Kittrell College, Limestone College, Lincoln Hospital Nurses' Home, Lincoln Memorial University, North Carolina College for Negroes, Wofford College, and the YWCA (Durham, NC). Also includes Duke's letter of resignation as president of the Erwin Cotton Mills and endorsement of William A. Erwin as his replacement (1927 January 10).
    - 1929 and circa 1920s, 1 folders (Box 62)
      Includes a typescript notice of funeral for Benjamin N. Duke, arrangements for train chartered to bring mourners to Durham from New York, contributions to Lincoln Memorial University in Duke's memory by Sarah P. Duke and Mary Duke Biddle, and copy of a memorial resolution from the Board of Trustees of Elon College.
    - 1932-1934, 1936-1941, 2 folders (Box 62)
      Letters dated 1932 and later are primarily solicitatons made by North Carolina institutions that Benjamin N. Duke supported during his lifetime, including Kittrell College, the North Carolina College for Negroes, Lincoln Hospital, and West Durham Methodist Church. Also included is a letter from Ora J. Swing to Doris Duke Cromwell, describing the friendship of Kate Reynolds, Swing's mother, with Benjamin and Mary Duke at New Garden School in 1871-1872. Swing enclosed a letter written by Benjamin to Kate dated June 24, 1872, the original of which is filed chronologically in the Correspondence series, folder "1872, 1877, 1879."
    - Condolences, Angier B. Duke, 1923-1924; 2 folders (Box 62)
      These folders contain a disbound volume of typescript copies of condolences sent to Benjamin and Sarah Duke on the death of Angier B. Duke. An alphabetical index of correspondents is included.
  - Letterbooks, 1892-1923
    The fragile letterbooks consist of bound carbon-copies of outgoing correspondence as well as scattered financial statements. Most letterbooks include alphabetical indexes of correspondents. Letters from Duke's Durham and New York offices are bound separately, with some overlap in time periods covered. As correspondents directed letters to city in which Duke was thought to presently inhabit, correspondence issued by either office of origin was not limited to topics particular to that location.
    There are also occasional outgoing letters from Angier B. Duke and Washington Duke, with the latter correspondence mainly concerning responses to requests for financial assistance.
    The letterbooks are arranged chronologically for each office of origin, with Durham office letterbooks listed first.
    Fragile—please ask for staff assistance in handling these items.
    - 1892 April 7-1893 February 22 (Durham office) (Volume 14)
    - 1893 February 25-December 30 (Durham office) (Volume 15)
    - 1894 January 1-August 29 (Durham office) (Volume 16)
    - 1894 August 29-1895 April 8 (Durham office) (Volume 17)
    - 1895 April 8-November 11 (Durham office) (Volume 18)
    - 1895 November 11-1896 May 11 (Durham office) (Volume 19)
    - 1896 May 11-December 7 (Durham office) (Volume 20)
    - 1896 December 9-1897 May 7 (Durham office) (Volume 21)
    - 1897 May 8-1898 May 14 (Durham office) (Volume 22)
    - 1898 May 16-1899 August 9 (Durham office) (Volume 23)
    - 1899 August 14-1901 March 18 (Durham office) (Volume 24)
    - 1901 March 19-1903 April 4 (Durham office) (Volume 25)
    - 1903 April 9-1906 October 15 (Durham office) (Volume 26)
    - 1906 December 1-1910 May 6 (Durham office) (Volume 27)
    - 1910 May 9-1911 March 16 (Durham office) (Volume 28)
    - 1911 March 17-1913 September 19 (Durham office) (Volume 29)
    - 1913 September 23-1917 February 28 (Durham office) (Volume 30)
    - 1917 March 1-1923 April 21 (Durham office) (Volume 31)
    - 1909 November 27-1910 September 7 (New York office) (Volume 32)
    - 1910 September 7-1911 May 17 (New York office) (Volume 33)
    - 1911 May 18-1912 January 23 (New York office) (Volume 34)
    - 1912 January 23-July 15 (New York office) (Volume 35)
    - 1912 July 16-1913 February 20 (New York office) (Volume 36)
    - 1913 February 20-1913 September 20 (New York office) (Volume 37)
    - 1913 September 17-1914 June 24 (New York office) (Volume 38)
    - 1914 June 25-1915 April 8 (New York office) (Volume 39)
    - 1915 April 12-1916 January 8 (New York office) (Volume 40)
    - 1916 January 11-1916 September 18 (New York office) (Volume 41)
    - 1916 September 18-1917 April 2 (New York office) (Volume 42)
    - 1917 April 2-1917 September 11 (New York office) (Volume 43)
    - 1917 September 12-1918 April 25 (New York office) (Volume 44)
- Financial, 1876-1878, 1884-1936, and undated; 30.5 Linear Feet
  The materials in the Financial series reflect the personal, business and philanthropic interests of Benjamin Newton Duke. Types of records present include bills, charitable contributions, check stubs, invoices, statements of accounts, tax statements, receipts, stock transactions, trial balances, household and petty cash accounts, brokerage account statements and correspondence. Materials related to the finances of James B. Duke include financial statements and correspondence of the Southern Investment Company of Canada and scattered, miscellaneous statements.
  B. N. Duke's financial ledgers and official bookkeeping responsibilities were transferred from his Durham office to his New York office in May 1901.
  The materials in this series are arranged into three subseries: General, Banking, and Investments.
  - General, 1876-1878, 1884-1936, and undated
    The General subseries contains materials related to the general financial transactions of Benjamin N. Duke and his family. The bills, invoices, receipts, and invoice books at the beginning of the subseries are primarily related to household and personal expenditures in Durham, NC and New York, NY. Also represented in the General subseries are transactions involving domestic and international travel for personal and business purposes; medical expenses; automobile purchases and maintenance; art and personal photograph purchases; loans to and from B.N. Duke, including repayments and interest payments; construction of and improvements to residences in Durham and New York; construction of and improvements to Trinity College buildings and grounds; agricultural and construction supplies for Duke's farm in Orange County, NC; and financial contributions to Trinity College and other philanthropic interests of the Duke family.
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1884-1899; 14 folders (Box 64)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1900-1901 April 15; 13 folders (Box 65)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1901 April 16-1902 April; 14 folders (Box 66)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1902 May-1903 December; 18 folders (Box 67)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1904 January-1905 December; 21 folders (Box 68)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1906 January-1907 July; 19 folders (Box 69)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1907 August-1908 September; 14 folders (Box 70)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1908 October-1909 July; 17 folders (Box 71)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1909 August-1910 April; 14 folders (Box 72)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1910 May-1910 December; 15 folders (Box 73)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1911 January-August; 15 folders (Box 74)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1911 September-1912 March; 13 folders (Box 75)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1912 April-October; 13 folders (Box 76)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1912 November-1913 April; 12 folders (Box 77)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1913 May-September; 13 folders (Box 78)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1913 October-1914 April; 14 folders (Box 79)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1914 May-November; 14 folders (Box 80)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1914 December-1916 May; 17 folders (Box 81)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1916 June-1918 August; 15 folders (Box 82)
    - Bills, invoices, receipts, 1918 September-1923 December, and undated; 14 folders (Box 83)
    - Invoices, 1906 March-April; oversize (Box 123, Folder 7)
      Commissary charges, Pullman Car Company (1906); Rolls Royce automobile order form (Angier B. Duke) (1912).
    - Invoice book, 1892-1893; 3 folders (Box 84)
    - Invoice book, 1893-1898, vol. 1 (includes index), 7 folders; disbound volume (Box 85)
    - Invoice book, 1893-1898, vol. 2, 7 folders; disbound volume (Box 86)
    - Cashbook, 1892 March-1904 December (Box 166)
    - Cashbook No. 2, 1905-1914 (Box 163)
    - Cashbook No. 3, 1915 January - 1917 November (Volume 1)
    - Cashbook No. 4, 1917 December - 1922 November (Volume 2)
    - Cashbook No. 5, 1922 December - 1928 July (Volume 3)
    - Cashbook No. 6, 1928 August - 1929 January (Volume 4)
    - Cashbook, Estate of Angier B. Duke, deceased, 1923-1926 (Volume 5)
    - Journal No. 1 ("Real Estate"), 1913 December - 1915 May (Volume 6)
    - Journal No. 2 ("New York"), 1905 December-1914 December (Volume 7)
    - Journal No. 3 ("New York"), 1915 January-1919 June (Box 167)
    - Journal No. 4, 1919 July-1924 August (Volume 8)
    - Journal No. 5, 1924 September-1929 January (Volume 9)
    - Private journal, 1892 March-1905 December (Box 164)
    - Private ledger [Ledger No. 1], 1892 March - 1901 July (Volume 10)
    - Ledger No. 4, 1915 January - 1922 December (Volume 11)
    - Ledger No. 5, 1923 January - 1926 November (Volume 12)
    - Ledger, special account no. 2 (Sarah P. Duke), 1926 February-1937 December (Volume 13)
    - Account book, 1901-1910 (Box 165)
    - Account book: Brodie L. Duke tobacco purchases, 1876 October-1878 January (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Bethany Sunday School: treasurer's (B. N. Duke) report and account, 1893-1894 (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - Cash statements: Benjamin N. Duke and family, 1917 January-May (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - Charitable contributions: 1892-1928, circa 1928; typescript lists (Box 87, Folder 4)
      The list of total charitable contributions from 1892 through 1928 is arranged by category of institution: schools, churches, hospitals, orphanages and miscellaneous. The list of annual charitable contributions for the years 1925-1928 is arranged alphabetically by institution name. Also included is a list of dividends for investments made on behalf of North Carolina institutions, acquaintances and family members.
    - [Duke] Memorial Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Durham, NC: financial statements and statistical report, 1911, 1913 (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - Gifts to Roney-Duke relatives, 1925-1927 (Box 87, Folder 6)
      These materials are related to Benjamin N. Duke's effort in the mid-1920s to identify and provide financial gifts to relatives on the Duke and Roney sides of the family. They include tables of disbursments made to family members and correspondence with Alexander H. Sands, Jr. related to the project. As the family research was later used to settle claims against the James B. Duke estate, related correspondence can found in the James Buchanan Duke Papers: Correspondence and Estate series.
    - Insurance policies, 1912-1914, 1924 (Box 87, Folder 7)
    - Insurance policies, 1893, 1913-1914; oversize (Box 123, Folder 8)
      Entities covered by these policies include Benjamin N. Duke, Angier B. Duke, and the Fidelity Bank of Durham.
    - Interest statements, 1900 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    - Inventories: New York house: furniture and equipment; garage supplies and livery, 1907 (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Inventories: New York office furniture and fixtures, 1901-1909, 1911 (Box 87, Folder 10)
    - Inventory and expenses: Berkshire County, MA property, 1911-1912 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    - Louisburg Female College: report to North Carolina Conference, 1902 December 1 (Box 87, Folder 12)
    - Main Street Methodist Episcopal Church (Durham, NC), 1885-1886, 1888, 1900, 1911 (Box 87, Folder 13)
      The church documents include Building Committee minutes, bylaws, and correspondence related to the construction of the new church (completed 1887) and a 1911 condensed financial statement. The correspondence includes two June 1888 letters between Julian S. Carr and Benjamin N. Duke regarding subscriptions from the Trinity Methodist Church congregation.
    - North Carolina Children's Home Society: financial reports, 1906-1907, 1910, 1912, 1914 (Box 87, Folder 14)
    - Order book (automobile supplies), 1912 May-1913 April (Box 87, Folder 15)
    - Oxford Orphan Asylum: report to the Grand Lodge of NC, [1901] (Box 87, Folder 16)
    - Southern Power Company: financial report and statements, 1907, 1910-1913 (Box 87, Folder 17)
      The financial statements include statements of accounts with Benjamin N. Duke and condensed cash statements for the company's New York office.
    - Statements: Durham, NC monthly expenditures (J. E. Stagg, agent), 1902-1907 (Box 87, Folder 18)